<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Historical Document Analysis on VML-BGU</title><link>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/</link><description>Recent content in Historical Document Analysis on VML-BGU</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><atom:link href="https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arabic Paleography</title><link>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/arabic-paleography/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/arabic-paleography/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="overview"&gt;Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a detailed description of the Arabic Paleography sub-project&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="methods"&gt;Methods&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use Transformers and&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="publications"&gt;Publications&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;List of publications here&amp;hellip;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description></item><item><title>Document Alignment and Reconstruction</title><link>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/alignment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/alignment/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="project-overview"&gt;Project Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sub-project focuses on one of the most challenging problems in historical document analysis: reconstructing documents that have been damaged, torn, or fragmented over time. Our goal is to create a robust pipeline that can take images of fragments and automatically determine how they fit together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="technical-approach"&gt;Technical Approach&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are exploring a multi-stage approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feature Extraction:&lt;/strong&gt; Using deep learning models to identify unique patterns, ink strokes, and material features on the edges of fragments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pairwise Matching:&lt;/strong&gt; Implementing a graph-based algorithm to test potential matches between fragments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Global Optimization:&lt;/strong&gt; Solving a jigsaw-like puzzle to find the most probable overall document structure from all pairwise matches.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="challenges"&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Non-linear deformations of aged paper and parchment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Missing pieces and large gaps in the material.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fading ink and similar visual patterns across different fragments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="next-steps"&gt;Next Steps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are currently curating a novel dataset of artificially fragmented documents with ground truth alignment data to train and evaluate our models.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hebrew Paleography and Segmentation</title><link>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/hebrew-segmentation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nancyaq.github.io/vml-website/projects/historical-documents/hebrew-segmentation/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="project-overview"&gt;Project Overview&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to create accurate pixel-level segmentation of Hebrew manuscripts, distinguishing between text, decorations, annotations, and the document background. A key challenge is the complex, often degraded appearance of these historical sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="key-tasks"&gt;Key Tasks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Text/Background Separation:&lt;/strong&gt; Using U-Net architectures to create binary masks isolating text regions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scribal Hand Identification:&lt;/strong&gt; Going beyond simple segmentation, we are training models to classify different writing styles within the same document, which is crucial for textual scholars.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise and Degradation Handling:&lt;/strong&gt; Developing techniques that are robust to stains, bleed-through from the other side of the page, and physical damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id="datasets"&gt;Datasets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are working with digitized collections from the National Library of Israel and partnering with paleographers from the Department of Jewish History to create accurate ground truth labels.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>